<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>thisisyojan</title>
    <description>In a way, we're all spiders weaving the web.</description>
    <link>http://sinkingshriek.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://sinkingshriek.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>barebone unit testing in angular with mocha</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;tl;dr:- wanted to do testing in angular, found tuts that showed dep with karma, writing without one&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I’ve been trying to get my hands dirty on angular and while the tutorial in the official angular site showed some testing code, it never showed how to set one up. So, like any person I started googling for a quick tutorial on setting up unit testing for angular but every tutorial that I found wanted me to install &lt;code&gt;karma&lt;/code&gt; first. I’ve played with &lt;code&gt;karma&lt;/code&gt; before and didn’t really see the point of needing &lt;code&gt;karma&lt;/code&gt; for quick unit testing. As &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/vojtajina&quot; title=&quot;Creator of Karma&quot;&gt;Vojta Jina&lt;/a&gt; himself says, &lt;code&gt;karma&lt;/code&gt; is a test-runner, that’s it. It’s not required for your unit tests at all. It’s just something nice to have to automate the process. Below are the following things that you do indeed need:-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mochajs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;chaijs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the only two dependencies that you will be needing in your test code. *Of course if you’re using &lt;code&gt;jasmine&lt;/code&gt; you don’t need &lt;code&gt;chaijs&lt;/code&gt; either. But since I like freedom and &lt;code&gt;chaijs&lt;/code&gt; allows me to use any assertion library I’m gonna go ahead and use that with &lt;code&gt;mochajs&lt;/code&gt; which is just a testing &lt;code&gt;wrapper&lt;/code&gt; without any &lt;code&gt;assertion&lt;/code&gt; (that’s why chai is for).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can download &lt;code&gt;mocha&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;chai&lt;/code&gt; with npm but for simplicity’s sake I’m gonna go ahead and just point those to cdn.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setup&quot;&gt;Setup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You would need:-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;index.html
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#mocha&quot;&gt;mochajs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chai&quot;&gt;chaijs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#angular&quot;&gt;angularjs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#mocha&quot;&gt;div with &lt;code&gt;mocha&lt;/code&gt; id in it&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#testing-style-with-optional-assertions&quot;&gt;testing style setup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#code-to-be-tested&quot;&gt;your_app_code.js&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#test-code&quot;&gt;your_test_code.js&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#running-the-tests&quot;&gt;run mocha&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The order for:-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;angularjs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mochajs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;chaijs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;doesn’t really matter but &lt;code&gt;mocha setup&lt;/code&gt; has to come after &lt;code&gt;mochajs&lt;/code&gt;. The order for &lt;code&gt;your_app_code.js&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;your_test_code.js&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;run mocha&lt;/code&gt; &lt;strong&gt;absolutely matters&lt;/strong&gt;. Get that ordering wrong and you’ll spend almost 15 mins trying to debug what exactly is happening. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, let’s get started with the code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;code&quot;&gt;Code&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mocha&quot;&gt;mocha&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we’re doing this without &lt;code&gt;karma&lt;/code&gt; you would need a plain &lt;code&gt;html5&lt;/code&gt; file. We’re gonna go ahead and add &lt;code&gt;mochajs&lt;/code&gt; in the page with &lt;code&gt;mocha&lt;/code&gt; css and &lt;code&gt;div&lt;/code&gt; that &lt;code&gt;mocha&lt;/code&gt; requires which is in &lt;code&gt;line 10&lt;/code&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;jsbin-embed&quot; href=&quot;http://jsbin.com/fiqoze/1/embed?html&quot;&gt;MySite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;http://static.jsbin.com/js/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;chai&quot;&gt;chai&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s go ahead and add &lt;code&gt;chaijs&lt;/code&gt; too. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;jsbin-embed&quot; href=&quot;http://jsbin.com/fiqoze/2/embed?html&quot;&gt;MySite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;http://static.jsbin.com/js/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;testing-style-with-optional-assertions&quot;&gt;testing style with optional assertions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like to setup my &lt;code&gt;mocha setup&lt;/code&gt; after I include &lt;code&gt;mocha&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;chai&lt;/code&gt; because I’m adding &lt;code&gt;var assert = chai.assert&lt;/code&gt; which requires &lt;code&gt;chaijs&lt;/code&gt;. You could have added &lt;code&gt;var assert = chai.assert&lt;/code&gt; in your test code too but I like to add them in global. It makes sense to put them in global because istead of having them to write that over and over on each of our test files you just write once and if you do need some other assertion in your file you can also include them in your individual files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;jsbin-embed&quot; href=&quot;http://jsbin.com/fiqoze/3/embed?html&quot;&gt;MySite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;http://static.jsbin.com/js/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;angular&quot;&gt;angular&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now include &lt;code&gt;angular&lt;/code&gt; (You can change the version here. At the moment of writing this, this was the latest stable version).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;jsbin-embed&quot; href=&quot;http://jsbin.com/fiqoze/4/embed?html&quot;&gt;MySite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;http://static.jsbin.com/js/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;code-to-be-tested&quot;&gt;code to be tested&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, include the code that you want to test. This includes all your &lt;code&gt;controllers&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;services&lt;/code&gt; everything. Here, let’s assume that I have them all in my &lt;code&gt;app.js&lt;/code&gt; file. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;jsbin-embed&quot; href=&quot;http://jsbin.com/fiqoze/5/embed?html&quot;&gt;MySite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;http://static.jsbin.com/js/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;test-code&quot;&gt;test code&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We finally include our &lt;code&gt;spec&lt;/code&gt; file or &lt;code&gt;test&lt;/code&gt; file on our page (Usually, I put them under test folder which is like the standard convention now but you can put wherever you want depending on your preference).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;jsbin-embed&quot; href=&quot;http://jsbin.com/fiqoze/6/embed?html&quot;&gt;MySite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;http://static.jsbin.com/js/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;running-the-tests&quot;&gt;running the tests&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re not done yet. We have to now tell &lt;code&gt;mocha&lt;/code&gt; to run our &lt;code&gt;tests&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;jsbin-embed&quot; href=&quot;http://jsbin.com/fiqoze/7/embed?html&quot;&gt;MySite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;http://static.jsbin.com/js/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open this in Firefox or Chrome(if Chrome’s giving you problem with some security issues then switch to Firefox or run it with some simple server). And see your tests passing..or failing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you use &lt;code&gt;Sublime Text&lt;/code&gt; then you can also use the following snippet I made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/sinkingshriek/fa546d0e6d2fe06facb5.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2014 20:34:19 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://sinkingshriek.github.io/node/angular/chaijs/mocha/2014/07/27/barebones-unit-testing-in-angular-with-mocha/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sinkingshriek.github.io/node/angular/chaijs/mocha/2014/07/27/barebones-unit-testing-in-angular-with-mocha/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>when it's apt to use global</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Pretty much almost any programmer that you meet would say that sticking variables to &lt;code&gt;global&lt;/code&gt; object is a bad idea. JavaScript was pretty notorious for this one. Forget to put &lt;code&gt;var&lt;/code&gt; in your variable inside the &lt;code&gt;function&lt;/code&gt; and it goes straight to the &lt;code&gt;window&lt;/code&gt;(global) object if you forgot &lt;code&gt;'use strict';&lt;/code&gt; in your function or in global context. It’s still true for node but instead of &lt;code&gt;window&lt;/code&gt; object it gets added to &lt;code&gt;global&lt;/code&gt; object.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;Global&lt;/code&gt; is well, global object in node, just like &lt;code&gt;window&lt;/code&gt; in browsers. You can put your variables in global object by either not declaring it with &lt;code&gt;var&lt;/code&gt; or using &lt;code&gt;global&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;GLOBAL&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;em&gt;&lt;code&gt;GLOBAL&lt;/code&gt; is just an alias for global.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, let’s just demonstrate the above with some code. Create two files with the following content and then run &lt;code&gt;node index&lt;/code&gt;;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/sinkingshriek/7ac40170e5d2606b4180.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see from the above code that we didn’t really export &lt;code&gt;someVal&lt;/code&gt; from globalMe and yet the &lt;code&gt;index.js&lt;/code&gt; was still able to find it. And as you may have already guessed it, it’s because that we’re sticking this into &lt;code&gt;global&lt;/code&gt; object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, so enough of the demonstration and to get to the point on the real topic at hand. Why would we ever want to use it if it’s a bad practice?&lt;br /&gt;
There are times when you just can’t avoid using &lt;code&gt;global&lt;/code&gt; object. Just recently I &lt;em&gt;had&lt;/em&gt; to use &lt;code&gt;global&lt;/code&gt; object to get my code running which brings me to another topic.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-use-chaijs-in-your-mochaopts-&quot;&gt;How to use chaijs in your mocha.opts ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t go into details on what &lt;code&gt;chai&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;mocha&lt;/code&gt; is in this post. And if you’ve been playing around with mocha then you know you can have &lt;code&gt;mocha.opts&lt;/code&gt; file in your &lt;code&gt;test&lt;/code&gt; folder which is basically options for your &lt;code&gt;mocha&lt;/code&gt; command. So instead of doing:-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;mocha --required should --reporter nyan
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can do :-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;//mocha.opts
--required should
--reporter nyan
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But since &lt;code&gt;chaijs&lt;/code&gt; is a bundle of three different assertion libraries you can’t do &lt;code&gt;mocha --required chai().should&lt;/code&gt;. That’s just absurd. Your command line doesn’t invoke functions. So how do you go about achieving &lt;code&gt;chai&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code&gt;mocha&lt;/code&gt;? Globals!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you create a &lt;code&gt;node_module&lt;/code&gt; with some file called..let’s say &lt;code&gt;chai-mocha-wrap.js&lt;/code&gt; with the following globals :-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/sinkingshriek/40e6cd6728e0c39e883d.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then you should be able to do :-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;//mocha.opts
--required chai-mocha
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And have chai assertion on all your mocha tests. You also have the option to use &lt;code&gt;should&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;expect&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;assert&lt;/code&gt; (yay freedom!!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although, this is an ideal case for the usage of &lt;code&gt;global&lt;/code&gt; you should always, &lt;strong&gt;always&lt;/strong&gt; document why you’re using &lt;code&gt;global&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jul 2014 20:34:19 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://sinkingshriek.github.io/node/chaijs/mocha/2014/07/13/apt-use-of-global/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sinkingshriek.github.io/node/chaijs/mocha/2014/07/13/apt-use-of-global/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Creating chains </title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Just a quick tip this week. Although, most of you know about &lt;code&gt;this&lt;/code&gt; already, you can return your prototype function with &lt;code&gt;this&lt;/code&gt; to make them chainable.
Below is the snippet that will enable that:-
&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/sinkingshriek/f12bb33a19e383c3ec53.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is technically what jQuery uses for their functions to be chainable and I just recently found out about. Makes your code lot more dynamic this way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2014 20:34:19 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://sinkingshriek.github.io/javascript/protip/2014/07/09/creating-chains/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sinkingshriek.github.io/javascript/protip/2014/07/09/creating-chains/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>exports vs module.exports</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been out for quite some time not just two weeks as I had mentioned in my last post. I decided to take a break from coding and travel a bit. I now officially love Boston, in summer atleast. Of course this is not relevant to what the topic at hand is but if you were like me who spends pretty much his entire life in front of computer then I encourage you to go travel and see new places. It will definitely open up your mind to new things. With that insightful words about life, let’s now dive into what exports and module.exports actually does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll assume that you already know basics of how NodeJS uses modules, if not then I highly recommend taking a look at &lt;a href=&quot;http://wiki.commonjs.org/wiki/Modules/1.1.1&quot;&gt;CommonJS&lt;/a&gt; module which NodeJS follows.&lt;br /&gt;
So, you’ve seen people use both &lt;code&gt;exports&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;module.exports&lt;/code&gt; while exporting their module. Before that, let’s first uncover on what really gets exported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-really-gets-exported&quot;&gt;What really gets exported&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quite simply, &lt;code&gt;module.exports&lt;/code&gt; is the only thing that gets exported. So how exactly does &lt;code&gt;exports&lt;/code&gt; export the module? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;exports-is-just-a-global-reference-to-moduleexports&quot;&gt;exports is just a global reference to module.exports&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you understand how referencing works in JavaScript then this is straight forward. &lt;code&gt;exports&lt;/code&gt; is just pointing &lt;code&gt;module.exports&lt;/code&gt; which is why you cannot reference functions or any other objects to it, if you do, then whatever that you were trying to export will simply not work because the reference has been broken. Let’s look at an example:-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;function Calculator(x,y){
	this.x = x;
	this.y = y;
}
Calculate.prototype = {
	constructor: Calculator,
	add : function(){
		return this.x + this.y;
	},
	subtract: function(){
		return this.x - this.y;
	}
}

exports = Calculator; // This will not work.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t worry about the code so much except the last line. The reason that it fails, as said above, is because it’s now referencing the &lt;code&gt;Calculator&lt;/code&gt; function and since &lt;code&gt;module.exports&lt;/code&gt; is the only thing that gets exported &lt;code&gt;exports&lt;/code&gt; just sits there not knowing what to do. However, do note that the following however works:-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;function Calculator(x,y){
	this.x = x;
	this.y = y;
}
Calculate.prototype = {
	constructor: Calculator,
	add : function(){
		return this.x + this.y;
	},
	subtract: function(){
		return this.x - this.y;
	}
}

exports.Calculator = Calculator; //This will however work.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think for a moment on why the above works. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you remove the veil of &lt;code&gt;exports&lt;/code&gt; then the above code is essentially doing the following:-  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;module.exports.Calculator = Calculator;  
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Since you haven’t really broken the reference of &lt;code&gt;exports&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;module.exports&lt;/code&gt; and only adding properties to &lt;code&gt;module.exports&lt;/code&gt; the above code should work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you really want to use &lt;code&gt;exports&lt;/code&gt; and be able to reference it to your function then you can also do this:-  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;module.exports = exports = Calculator;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that clarifies a little on &lt;code&gt;module.exports&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;exports&lt;/code&gt; to you. It’s just a little concept but I had the hardest time figuring out why some uses one over another. &lt;code&gt;module.exports&lt;/code&gt; is more elegant way to export the module because it’s “OOP” way. Don’t take my word for it that’s what people say. :)&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jun 2014 20:34:19 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://sinkingshriek.github.io/casual/node/modules/2014/06/28/exports-vs-module-exports/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sinkingshriek.github.io/casual/node/modules/2014/06/28/exports-vs-module-exports/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ranges in npm.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ll keep this post really short as I have been quite busy and will still be for the next two weeks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, this week in one of the JS meetup &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mrjedmao&quot;&gt;Jed Mao&lt;/a&gt; brought up a really good point on why he uses &lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt; from the &lt;code&gt;cli&lt;/code&gt; instead of writing the package name in &lt;code&gt;package.json&lt;/code&gt; and just doing &lt;code&gt;npm install&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to make any sense of the paragraph below then make sure that you know what &lt;a href=&quot;http://semver.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;semver&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I put forth his reasoning, I was all up for just writing our &lt;code&gt;deps&lt;/code&gt; in &lt;code&gt;package.json&lt;/code&gt; and just doing &lt;code&gt;npm install&lt;/code&gt; from the cli. But there are something called &lt;code&gt;ranges&lt;/code&gt; that you can specify in the version number for your dependencies so that only those dependencies that are in the range gets downloaded. The comprehensive list of ranges is posted at the link below but in summary here are the ranges that you can specify :-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;1.0.0&lt;/code&gt; :-&lt;br /&gt;
greater than a specific version number. You can also use &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;=&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;=&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;1.0.0  &amp;lt;2.0.0&lt;/code&gt; || &lt;code&gt;1.0.0 - 2.0.0&lt;/code&gt; :-&lt;br /&gt;
whatever the version between v1 and v2. You can use the first or the second one. Again, you can use &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;=&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;=&lt;/code&gt; likewise.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;~1.0.0&lt;/code&gt; :-&lt;br /&gt;
accepts all patches, meaning &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;=1.0.1 - &amp;lt;1.1.0&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;^1.0.0&lt;/code&gt; :-&lt;br /&gt;
accepts all pre-releases (minor release), meaning &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;=1.0.0 - &amp;lt;2.0.0&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;1.0.x&lt;/code&gt; || &lt;code&gt;1.0.*&lt;/code&gt; || &lt;code&gt;1.0&lt;/code&gt; :-&lt;br /&gt;
accepts all the version that matches &lt;code&gt;1.0&lt;/code&gt; versions&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; || &lt;code&gt;x&lt;/code&gt; || &lt;code&gt;&quot;&quot;&lt;/code&gt; :-&lt;br /&gt;
any version whatsoever (usually the recent one)  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last one on the list was my proposal to include in the &lt;code&gt;package.json&lt;/code&gt; file so that one doesn’t have to go lookup the version number for each &lt;code&gt;dep&lt;/code&gt;. But like Jed pointed out it can have bad consequences and I was naive to even think &lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; was an option. &lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; means all the major, minor and patches. Major changes could mean that it will break your application if you rely on version specific features. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, Jed’s advice made perfect sense to me. His advice was to just use &lt;code&gt;cli&lt;/code&gt; like so :-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;npm install express mongodb mocha sinon grunt&lt;/code&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing the above will install the latest stable build and npm will also put the actual version name with &lt;code&gt;^&lt;/code&gt; at the prefix. Again, &lt;code&gt;^&lt;/code&gt; will install all the pre-releases and should not break your application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To keep track of your versions you can also use &lt;a href=&quot;https://gemnasium.com/&quot;&gt;Gemnasium&lt;/a&gt; as mentioned by Jed in the meetup. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/isaacs/node-semver#ranges&quot;&gt;More about ranges from Issac.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2014 21:34:19 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://sinkingshriek.github.io/node/npm/2014/06/06/ranges-in-npm/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sinkingshriek.github.io/node/npm/2014/06/06/ranges-in-npm/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How node modules actually load.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ll take a break from the devtools post and post a quick info that I’ve been reading up this week.&lt;br /&gt;
Before jumping to the topic let’s first look at what module really is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, a module is nothing but a separated functionality (piece) of a program that gives structure to your code while adhering to two key features, &lt;strong&gt;low&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;code&gt;coupling&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;high&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;code&gt;cohesion&lt;/code&gt;, meaning that the piece of code that you write has very less or no dependency (&lt;strong&gt;low coupling&lt;/strong&gt;) and can be pluggable to almost any part of your other program (&lt;strong&gt;high cohesion&lt;/strong&gt;). Basically, these two terms go hand in hand and are co-related.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, think of node modules as just a JavaScript module and you plug these modules in your program like this:-  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;`var myModule = require(‘./myModule’);’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what the meat of this post is going to be. What exactly is happening when you do &lt;code&gt;require&lt;/code&gt;? Before I go any further notice that &lt;code&gt;./&lt;/code&gt; before the module name in that require? Whenever you supply &lt;code&gt;./&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;require&lt;/code&gt; then node will search for the module in the current working directory or also called &lt;code&gt;relative path&lt;/code&gt;. So if you had your file structure as follows:-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;--myRootDirectory
----index.js //let's say this is where your require('./myModule') is
----myModule.js
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then doing &lt;code&gt;./&lt;/code&gt; will immediately search inside the current directory. If you would feel like putting your modules in a directory then that’s perfectly fine too. Just add &lt;code&gt;./directory_name/myAnotherModule&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a similar note, you can also do:-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;var myModule = require('/myModule');&lt;/code&gt; //note the absence of &lt;code&gt;.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;for &lt;code&gt;absolute path&lt;/code&gt;. This looks at the root of your app instead of the current directory. So if you had:-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;--myRootDirectory
----myAnotherDirectory
------myModule.js //let's say this is where your require('/myAnotherModule') is
----index.js 
----myAnotherModule.js
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, do note that since node already expects a JavaScript file you don’t have to put the &lt;code&gt;.js&lt;/code&gt; extension at th end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that was with the &lt;code&gt;./&lt;/code&gt; and ‘/’ at the prefix of your module but there’s another mechanism node follows to look for your modules. If you don’t supply the &lt;code&gt;./&lt;/code&gt; at the prefix then the following steps is followed by node to search for your module.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Checks if it’s a core module.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Checks the module in &lt;code&gt;node_modules&lt;/code&gt; directory in the current directory and moves up one directory until the root of your app.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lastly checks in the path of &lt;code&gt;NODE_MODULE&lt;/code&gt; that’s specified in your system’s &lt;code&gt;environment variable&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At the end throws exception if nothing is found.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core module that node checks in the beginning are the core modules that node provides like &lt;code&gt;http&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;fs&lt;/code&gt; which will take precedence over any other steps.&lt;br /&gt;
If it’s not a core module then it starts looking for &lt;code&gt;node_modules&lt;/code&gt; until it reaches the root of your application. Something like this:-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;--myRootDirectory
--node_modules
----myModule.js
--lib
----myAnotherModule.js //you can require('myModule') here.
--index.js // and here require('myModule') will reside.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See how &lt;code&gt;lib&lt;/code&gt; directory doesn’t have &lt;code&gt;node_modules&lt;/code&gt; and it goes up one level in &lt;code&gt;myRootDirectory&lt;/code&gt; where it does have &lt;code&gt;node_modules&lt;/code&gt; directory which indeed has &lt;code&gt;myModule&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
Also, in the index.js, which is inside &lt;code&gt;myRootDirectory&lt;/code&gt; has &lt;code&gt;node_modules&lt;/code&gt; directory so it just immediately knows where &lt;code&gt;myModule&lt;/code&gt; is.&lt;br /&gt;
NOTE:- node doesn’t traverse down so if you had something like this:-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;--myRootDirectory
--node_modules
----myModule.js
--lib
----node_modules
------myInsideModule.js
----myAnotherModule.js //you can require('myInsideModule') here.
--index.js // but not here. THIS WILL NOT WORK require('myInsideModule')
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if your module is inside your system path (&lt;code&gt;ENVIRONMENT VARIABLE&lt;/code&gt;) then your module should load just fine. For Windows users it’s usually in 
&lt;code&gt;c:\Program Files\Node\lib&lt;/code&gt; and for Linux users just &lt;code&gt;echo PATH&lt;/code&gt; and google on how to add path in your &lt;code&gt;environment variable&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can play with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sinkingshriek/load_node_module&quot;&gt;sample node_modules&lt;/a&gt; that I’ve made ready for you play. Check out the commits too on what mistakes I made to learn from it.  &lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2014 21:34:19 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://sinkingshriek.github.io/node/2014/05/29/how-node-modules-load/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sinkingshriek.github.io/node/2014/05/29/how-node-modules-load/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Imagine trying to build a skyscraper with just a wrench.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Think of us, devs, as construction workers. Let’s just pretend for now that we’re construction workers. You’re given all these ideas and blueprints by architects and business folks and everything that’s needed for construction. You are provided with all the possible resources that you can possibly think of to get this herculean task done but the problem is that you have no clue how to operate those big cranes, excavators, forklifts etc but you’re an expert in using wrench. I’m not saying it’s completely useless, well maybe to screw things when one of the nuts come lose in those bigger machinery but the point is you need to learn tools if you’re even conceiving of making big web-apps. This doesn’t just apply to web-apps. This applies to pretty much in all fields. So you, as a web-developer better know your tools well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I’m going to split this post into multiple posts as it got much bigger than I expected.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;devtools&quot;&gt;DevTools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are plenty of tutorials, tips and tricks on dev tools in the Internet and this one isn’t going to be different either. I can’t stress this enough. Learn to master &lt;em&gt;DEVTOOLS&lt;/em&gt;. It might feel like people are trying to shove it down your throat and they’re right to do so as it’s a crucial part of being a web-developer. If you’re going to be a decent developer then not knowing this should be a crime. This post is not going to dive into details into all the possibilities that devtools has to offer but give you overview on what power it holds. However I will present the link to go deeper on them if you want to know more of the APIs. I will try to cover for both Firefox and Chrome (sorry IE) but not going to do one on one comparison. Oh and another disclaimer is that this is geared more towards PC so if you’re Mac user then the shortcut might be a little different. Usually, the &lt;code&gt;Ctrl&lt;/code&gt; is replaced with &lt;code&gt;Cmd&lt;/code&gt;. Okay, let’s begin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;opening-devtools&quot;&gt;Opening devtools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fastest way to get to the developer tools in either Chrome or Firefox is by pressing &lt;code&gt;Ctrl + Shift + I&lt;/code&gt;. Others might prefer &lt;code&gt;F12&lt;/code&gt; but I usually go for the former since &lt;code&gt;F12&lt;/code&gt; is much farther than those three keys. You can also take the old route of right clicking and selecting &lt;code&gt;Inspect Element&lt;/code&gt; which will open up your devtools with &lt;code&gt;Element panel&lt;/code&gt; being active and focusing on the element that was pointed to by your mouse (assuming that the mouse click is on your browser). There are also other ways to open your devtools like going to the Settings -&amp;gt; Tools -&amp;gt; Developer Tools in Chrome or Tools -&amp;gt; Wev Developer -&amp;gt; Toggle Tools in Firefox. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;changing-settings-of-devtools&quot;&gt;Changing Settings of devtools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shortcut:-
&lt;em&gt;In Chrome only&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;code&gt;?&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;F1&lt;/code&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
You have your devtools open and before you do anything I highly, highly recommend you change some of the settings first. I’ve seen many people never enter settings even after their heavy usage of devtools. There are some really powerful options available under that settings. All you have to do is press that &lt;code&gt;gear icon&lt;/code&gt; on your devtools in Chrome and in Firefox or if you’re in Chrome then you can just use the shortcut provided above. The options might not be at the exact place in Firefox and Chrome but if you read through some of them then it’s not that hard to make connections between them. Also, not all options of one browser is guaranteed to be available in another, so depending on what you want you might favor one over another. But that’s a different topic on it’s own let’s just change some settings for now:-  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Disable Cache &lt;em&gt;//this way your browser doesn’t cache your js and css so that you can changes promptly after changes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The following pertains only to Chrome DevTools&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enable Ctrl + 1 - 9 shortcut to switch panels (self-explanatory which lets you jump to the tabs by pressing &lt;code&gt;Ctrl + [numeric key]&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#workspace_tab&quot;&gt;Workspaces tab&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;//if you want to live code on Chrome which is discussed later&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#shortcuts&quot;&gt;Shortcuts&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;//Learn those shortcuts for maximum efficiency, also discussed later&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Got your settings all setup? Alright, let’s start digging those hidden treasures that devtools has to offer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;console-tab&quot;&gt;Console Tab&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shortcuts:-&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;In Firefox&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Ctrl + Shift + K&lt;/code&gt; &lt;em&gt;//this will take you straight to the Web Console even if you’re in devtools (You’ll soon know why I mentioned this)&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Ctrl + Shift + J&lt;/code&gt; &lt;em&gt;//this will only bring up the Web console window and nothing else.&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In Chrome&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Ctrl + Shift + J&lt;/code&gt; &lt;em&gt;//to jump straight to Web Console from your normal browser. Invoking this shortcut again in the devtools will open another devtools for your devtools. This will go as deep as your mind will let you.&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Ctrl + 9&lt;/code&gt; &lt;em&gt;//if you’re already in devtools and has enabled &lt;code&gt;Ctrl 1-9 shortcut to switch panels&lt;/code&gt; as mentioned above.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re a JavaScript developer then you will be spending majority of your time here. So let’s start from this tab. The console acts like an interpreter and display all the logging informations. You can pretty much do your full programming here too (although not recommended). Go ahead and start writing your JavaScript expressions and start executing it (&lt;code&gt;Enter to execute&lt;/code&gt;) and (&lt;code&gt;Shift + Enter&lt;/code&gt;) to enter multi-line. Before we go full on on what this console has to offer take your time to right-click on the console and see what options it gives you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In Firefox&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Right click will give you option to &lt;code&gt;log requests and response bodies&lt;/code&gt;. What this means is it &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In Chrome&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Right click will give you more options than Firefox although you’re not losing any functionality per se.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Preserve the logs upon navigation&lt;br /&gt;
This does exactly what it says, if you’re jumping over pages then instead of clearing the console on every new page it stores your earlier logs for you.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Log XMLHttpRequest&lt;br /&gt;
This is to log your AJAX requests just in case if you ever needed that even though it’s available in &lt;code&gt;Network tab&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay okay, no more transients. Diving in console now.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;clear-console&quot;&gt;Clear console&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shortcut&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;code&gt;Ctrl + L&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Alternatives&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clear();&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Right click -&amp;gt; Clear console &lt;em&gt;In chrome&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clicking the clear icon in the devtools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the easiest way to clear the console is to just press &lt;code&gt;Ctrl + L&lt;/code&gt;. That’s it. You don’t have to type &lt;code&gt;clear()&lt;/code&gt; or right click and click &lt;code&gt;Clear Console&lt;/code&gt; or find any obscure icons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;last-evaluated-expression-1&quot;&gt;Last Evaluated expression &lt;code&gt;$_1&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before you go there and start trying this thing out in your console make sure what expression is. Basically, expressions are any valid code that resolves to a value. According to MDN, there are two types of expressions. Those that assign a value to a variable and those that are simple value.&lt;br /&gt;
So this:-&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;x = 1&lt;/code&gt; would be first type expression and &lt;code&gt;1+1&lt;/code&gt; would be second type expression. More on this &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Guide/Expressions_and_Operators&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, doing &lt;code&gt;$_&lt;/code&gt; should be pretty clear now that you understand what expression is. Again, &lt;code&gt;$_&lt;/code&gt; will return the last evaluated expression in the console. To be honest, I don’t use this as much. Pressing &lt;code&gt;up&lt;/code&gt; arrow is far more easier than typing &lt;code&gt;$_&lt;/code&gt;. But, just in case you need this then you know there’s a way to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;last-five-dom-elements-0---4&quot;&gt;Last five DOM elements &lt;code&gt;$0 - $4&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Say, you just inspected (right-click on website and select Inspect) something on your website and you want to grab that element. You could do &lt;code&gt;document.querySelector('some-class-or-id-or-tag')&lt;/code&gt; but why waste time when you can just do &lt;code&gt;$0&lt;/code&gt;. Do that again and the item that was stored in &lt;code&gt;$0&lt;/code&gt; earlier will move to &lt;code&gt;$1&lt;/code&gt; and so on till &lt;code&gt;$4&lt;/code&gt;. It’s not necessary that you have to inspect the element every-time from the website. You can simply select it on &lt;code&gt;Element Panel&lt;/code&gt; if you already know where that element is and then use it on console with &lt;code&gt;$0&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;query-selectors&quot;&gt;Query Selectors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;$(selector)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;$$(selector)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;$x(path) &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;selector&quot;&gt;$(selector)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, you know how to get the DOM elements using &lt;code&gt;$0 - $4&lt;/code&gt; but let’s say you have to find out the elements with certain selector. You could inspect all the elements in the site or even search (&lt;code&gt;Ctrl+F&lt;/code&gt;) in &lt;code&gt;Element panel&lt;/code&gt; but that’s tedious. But wait, you know some JavaScript. So you can just do :-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;tbody&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;document.getElementById('some-selector');&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;/tbody&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;document.querySelector('some-selector');&lt;/code&gt; &lt;em&gt;//heads up this is not same as &lt;code&gt;document.getElementById()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, you could just use the alias of &lt;code&gt;document.querySelector('some-selector')&lt;/code&gt; in devtools which is &lt;code&gt;$('some-selector')&lt;/code&gt;. That’s it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;selector-1&quot;&gt;$$(selector)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You try doing &lt;code&gt;$(selector)&lt;/code&gt; but all you’re getting is just one result. And then you realize that it’s just doing what &lt;code&gt;document.querySelector()&lt;/code&gt; was doing and sighed at yourself. Now you need something aliased to &lt;code&gt;document.querySelectorAll()&lt;/code&gt;. And as you can already figure out from the heading that you can achieve just that by using &lt;code&gt;$$(selector)&lt;/code&gt; and it will list out an array of all the elements with that selector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;xpath&quot;&gt;$x(path)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you happen to know &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/XPath&quot;&gt;XPath&lt;/a&gt; then there’s this &lt;code&gt;$x(path)&lt;/code&gt; for you too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;events&quot;&gt;Events&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;getEventListeners(object)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;monitorEvents(object, [events])&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;unmonitorEvents( object, [events])&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;geteventlistenersobject&quot;&gt;getEventListeners(object)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so you’re quite happy with what you have right now with all the query selectors at your disposal. And soon you realize that it’s about time to put some interactivity to your webpage. The most common thing to put interactivity in the webpage is to listen to any events in the page and act accordingly. Sure, if it’s a simple site, like this is, there may not be too much event in the page but as your webpage start getting more complex it’ll be crucial to know what event is called on a specific element. Again, you could do it manually and go to your editor and start searching for it or you could use tools that devtools provide you and be more productive. &lt;code&gt;getEventListenters(object)&lt;/code&gt; is just the function that helps you pinpoint what function is being invoked on the specified event. Let’s look at an example on how it works.
Syntax:-
&lt;code&gt;getEventListeners(DOM object,[events]);&lt;/code&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;getEventListeners(document.querySelector('testme'), &quot;click&quot;);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
What the above statement does is, it lists out the click event for the &lt;code&gt;testme&lt;/code&gt; element. Of course, you could use &lt;code&gt;$('testme')&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;$0&lt;/code&gt; to get that element but I’ll leave it up to you to be creative with what you can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above returns a click object for that element and the function that will be invoked in the &lt;code&gt;listener&lt;/code&gt; key.&lt;br /&gt;
Remember, the event parameter is totally optional. If you don’t specify it then it will return all the event that’s attached to that element.&lt;br /&gt;
Do note however, that if you’re adding listenter with &lt;code&gt;jquery&lt;/code&gt; then the &lt;code&gt;listener&lt;/code&gt; will display &lt;code&gt;jquery's&lt;/code&gt; wrapper function than yours. This deserves a post on it’s own so I’m not going to dwell more on it but if you want to list the listener that’s been done purely by &lt;code&gt;addEventListener&lt;/code&gt; then &lt;code&gt;getEventListeners&lt;/code&gt; should be more than enough. If you want to play more then here’s the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jsfiddle.net/shriek/QXC5B/&quot;&gt;fiddle&lt;/a&gt; for you. (Note that since jsfiddle uses iframe you might not be able to find the element)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;monitoreventsobjectevents&quot;&gt;monitorEvents(object,[events])&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far you’ve learned how to get elements with aliased query selectors, list the functions that will get invoked on events. But once-a-while there will come a time when your event will get triggered when it’s not supposed to causing all kinds of weird behaviors. For that very instance you can use &lt;code&gt;monitorEvents()&lt;/code&gt; function. This does exactly what it says. It simply monitors the events and logs whenever the event gets triggered on the specified element. Looking back to our earlier example let’s now monitor events on that click now.
&lt;code&gt;monitorEvents(document.querySelector('testme'), 'click');&lt;/code&gt;
This will log out Mouse Event object. According to the Paul Irish which was posted on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.briangrinstead.com/blog/chrome-developer-tools-monitorevents&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If the second argument is ‘mouse’, you’ll get all “mousedown”, “mouseup”, “click”, “dblclick”, “mousemove”, “mouseover”, “mouseout”, “mousewheel” events&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If the second argument is ‘key’, you’ll get all “keydown”, “keyup”, “keypress”, “textInput” events&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If the second argument is ‘touch’, you’ll get all “touchstart”, “touchmove”, “touchend”, “touchcancel” events. (See emulate touch events in devtools settings!!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If the second argument is ‘control’, you’ll get all “resize”, “scroll”, “zoom”, “focus”, “blur”, “select”, “change”, “submit”, “reset” events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you don’t define a second argument, you’ll get all of the above, plus… “load”, “unload”, “abort”, “error”, “select”, “change”, “submit”, “reset”, “focus”, “blur”, “resize”, “scroll”, “search”, “devicemotion”, “deviceorientation” .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The comment above should sum up the monitorEvents for you if not then here’s the official docs on:-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.chrome.com/devtools/docs/commandline-api#monitoreventsobject-events&quot;&gt;Chrome&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://getfirebug.com/wiki/index.php/MonitorEvents#Event_groups&quot;&gt;Firefox&lt;/a&gt; (even though it’s doc for firebug, I think they’re fairly similar)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;unmonitoreventsobject-events&quot;&gt;unmonitorEvents(object, [events])&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you want to stop monitoring for events then you can just use this function to stop listening. Also, you can stop listening to any one specific event if you were listening to multiple events. An example:-
&lt;code&gt;monitorEvents(document.querySelector('.testme'), 'mouse')&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;code&gt;unmonitorEvents(document.querySelector('.testme'),'mouseover')&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;copy&quot;&gt;copy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often times whenever I’m trying to debug &lt;code&gt;json&lt;/code&gt; objects I have to copy the response or just have to search if the key exists or not. Sure I could just do &lt;code&gt;key in jsonResponseObj&lt;/code&gt; or other techniques but this is about copying the values from console to your clipboard. Simple, just do :-
&lt;code&gt;copy(anything-that-you-want-to-copy)&lt;/code&gt;
That’s all there is to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;keysobj&quot;&gt;keys(obj)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to just list out the keys instead of checking it with &lt;code&gt;in&lt;/code&gt; keyword then you can just &lt;code&gt;keys&lt;/code&gt; function to list out all keys in your object.
keys({‘hey’: ‘there’, ‘how’:’you’}); // [‘hey’, ‘how’]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;valuesobj&quot;&gt;values(obj)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opposite to &lt;code&gt;keys&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;values&lt;/code&gt; is used to list out all the values in an object.
&lt;code&gt;values({'hey': 'there', 'how':'you'})&lt;/code&gt; &lt;em&gt;//will result in [‘there’, ‘you’]&lt;/em&gt; 
You can simple do the following to check if certain value exists or not if you want something similar to &lt;code&gt;in&lt;/code&gt; for values.
&lt;code&gt;values({'hey': 'there', 'how':'you'}).indexOf('hey') &amp;gt; -1&lt;/code&gt; &lt;em&gt;//true&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides mentioned above there are lot of things that console API is capable of doing simply because it is quite extensive and also because the docs are much more better at it. Also the API has slight variation on different browsers. Maybe in future I’ll point out some of the most useful functions but for now here are the docs.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/console&quot;&gt;Firefox Console API&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.chrome.com/devtools/docs/console-api&quot;&gt;Chrome Console API&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my next post I’ll be talking about &lt;code&gt;Debugger panel&lt;/code&gt;. Feel free to raise issues if you see something glaringly wrong in this post. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2014 20:34:19 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://sinkingshriek.github.io/casual/devtools/2014/05/23/imagine-trying-to-build-a-skyscrapper-with-just-a-hammer/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sinkingshriek.github.io/casual/devtools/2014/05/23/imagine-trying-to-build-a-skyscrapper-with-just-a-hammer/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Start of yet another another blog</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;For the longest time I’ve thought I should write down what goes in my head. Or at-least, document what I’m experimenting, reading or even one of those crazy shower ideas. It’s not that I didn’t try. Oh, I tried alright. I’ve tried &lt;em&gt;Blogger&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Wordpress&lt;/em&gt; and more &lt;em&gt;Wordpress&lt;/em&gt; but the thought of logging in (even though my browser logs them for me) and writing in their editor sounded too much of a work. If you’ve not figured out already, then yes, I am one lazy guy but I’ve got a good excuse to say that. I’m a programmer and it just didn’t feel right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then I heard about &lt;em&gt;pages&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;github&lt;/em&gt;. It sounded cool until I realize that it was just for static pages, of course you could commit your blog posts and it would appear as if it was a brand new posts but this too sounded too much of a work. Of course doing this is more work than signing up for a &lt;em&gt;Wordpress&lt;/em&gt; account but I still wanted to some control over and, well, &lt;em&gt;github&lt;/em&gt; did give me enough freedom to do so but it was a little overwhelming to be honest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the one thing that I’ve been overlooking all this time while browsing through the &lt;a href=&quot;http://pages.github.com&quot;&gt;pages.github.com&lt;/a&gt; was that it was using a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; engine, which has actually been for quite sometime (&lt;em&gt;spare me, I’ve been struggling with my life all these years and just getting in this field&lt;/em&gt;). This was just what I needed, not bare-bones, not too high-level. The middle-ground. Umm, yes. I could almost smell the victory with this, or is that my laptop fan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, what I’ve decided doing is to use both &lt;em&gt;pages.github.com&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;jekyll&lt;/em&gt; to run my blog. I’ve thought about using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.heroku.com&quot;&gt;heroku&lt;/a&gt; as my host too but I don’t see the reason to use &lt;em&gt;heroku&lt;/em&gt; when I already have &lt;em&gt;pages&lt;/em&gt;. And I recommend you do the same if you want to start your own blog and are in the similar situation as I am. Seriously, there is no excuse these days not too. There are too many tools that’s just ready for you to use. And if really really don’t want to start your own blog then I’ve made this blog open source, user can send me pull request on the topic if they want to be published. Now, if that’s not spoon feeding then I don’t know what is. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can send me a pull request at this &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sinkingshriek/jekyll-content&quot;&gt;project&lt;/a&gt; under _posts directory with filename as &lt;code&gt;YYYY-MM-DD-name-of-your-blog-title.md&lt;/code&gt;. You’re expected to know &lt;em&gt;markdown&lt;/em&gt; markup language. If you have no clue what that is then &lt;a href=&quot;http://markdowntutorial.com&quot;&gt;here’s a good starter&lt;/a&gt;. I’m using &lt;a href=&quot;http://kramdown.gettalong.org/quickref.html&quot;&gt;kramdown&lt;/a&gt; parser for my markdown so you might want to check that out too. Now, let us share the knowledge because as you know, it’s the only way to grow them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- You'll find this post in your `_posts` directory - edit this post and re-build (or run with the `-w` switch) to see your changes!
To add new posts, simply add a file in the `_posts` directory that follows the convention: YYYY-MM-DD-name-of-post.ext.

Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:
 --&gt;
&lt;!-- 
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Hi, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Tom&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#=&amp;gt; prints &amp;#39;Hi, Tom&amp;#39; to STDOUT.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


Check out the [Jekyll docs][jekyll] for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at [Jekyll's GitHub repo][jekyll-gh].

[jekyll-gh]: https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll
[jekyll]:    http://jekyllrb.com
 --&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2014 20:34:19 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://sinkingshriek.github.io/casual/2014/05/10/start-of-something-normal/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sinkingshriek.github.io/casual/2014/05/10/start-of-something-normal/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
